hey and welcome to the short stuff i'm josh and there's chuck and chuck i have a
question for you
yes don't you want to fanta is that a slogan
oh don't you wanna yeah yeah i remember that now it's very catchy
don't you fanna don't you wanna was that it don't you want to fanta
that's how i remember
yeah
oh okay uh i love fanna i mean wait wait you never answered my question well
yeah of course
i do if i love it okay um i think i've mentioned plenty of times that i did not
grow up drinking
much soda because as a family we didn't have the kind of money to just load up
the house with sodas
so sodas were only reserved for my mom to drink chab
oh yeah she was a tab drinker huh yeah we had money for that uh but i didn't
drink much soda
growing up so i don't drink soda now uh thankfully because that stuff is so bad
for you uh generally
speaking but i i will um hammer down six cokes a year and maybe four or five
fana oranges all at
once once a year i love them i love that fana orange i just you know you can't
drink that
stuff a lot have you had any of the other fantas the grape and etc
I think I like dabbled in the grape and knee-high grape and stuff when I was a
kid but it's really that and I like Sunkist preferred Sunkist as a kid here and
there Sunkist soda right yeah yeah but Fanta orange is one of my rare rare
guilty pleasures I gotcha I was more of a Faygo man as a kid I never drank those
and I also never have
drank any of the clear or yellows like I've never tasted Mountain Dew didn't
drink mellow yellow or Sprite or 7up or anything like that you missed out you've
never tasted Mountain Dew or mellow yellow I just want to make sure I have that
correct I don't think so wow I can't remember ever doing it I mean I don't even
know what it tastes like it looks lemon limey but no
no it's not it's its own thing for sure I don't know that you should ever break
the streak now that you've reached this long without trying it but it's not
lemon lime it's its own thing but what we're talking about is whether or not
Fanta is a Nazi drink
and we're going to go into the history of that and we're going to start out
talking a little bit about Coca-Cola the parent company as every most people
know by now it was invented by Dr. John Stith Pemberton in 1886 he was a
morphine addicted Civil War veteran looking for a better way to feel better than
morphine and put together some cocoa leaves and cola nuts which had you know
were stimulants because of cocaine and caffeine
and said hey this is like a new kind of medicine and after he died it went on to
be a very very popular drink it sure did one of the things that Coca-Cola did
over time was they expanded around the world they became an ambassador of
American democracy one of the places they expanded to is Germany pre-war Germany
or maybe interwar Germany I'm not sure when they showed up
but regardless by the time World War II was starting to ramp up say the 30s the
late 30s Coca-Cola was heavily entrenched in Germany and its subsidiary was
Coca-Cola GmbH which stands for Gelschaft mit Beschreiterhaftung which
translates to company with limited liability and there was a guy named Max Kite
who ran the show there
and boy oh boy was he dedicated to Coca-Cola and furthering the cause of Coca-
Cola in Germany yes for sure he there's a guy named Mark Pendergrast who wrote a
book called For God Country and Coca-Cola no colon yeah way to go Mark yeah
that's incredible
and he said that you know this guy loved coke so much he really just wanted to
weave it into every aspect of German life including the the Nazi Party even
though supposedly he never was officially joined the Nazi Party and you think
like well coke probably wasn't super stoked about this
they didn't care Robert Woodruff was running coke at the time and he was like
hey this is all good we're going to co-sponsor the 1936 Berlin Olympics we're
going to hang up some banners there with our logo right next to the swastika and
it's all it's all good everybody yeah can you imagine I looked high and low for
a photograph of that and I could not find it
I'm sure Coca-Cola has dedicated a significant amount of its operational funding
to destroying any evidence of that banner ever I haven't been to the world of
Coke Museum but I bet right here in Atlanta I bet it's not in there I'll bet
they don't have it up to there was also for the 10th anniversary of Coca-Cola
GMBH they decided to commemorate their deepest admiration for the Fuhrer for
Hitler's 50th birthday
with a mass Nazi salute I guess of employees who worked there at the time yeah
exactly so Coca-Cola was very much entrenched in Nazi Germany even before the
war especially before the war I should say well yeah because once the war
started uh we were like oh well I guess we can't do business with Germany
anymore right
and Germany was seizing enemy-owned businesses at will I think General Motors
actually got out of Germany but they did seize IBM and Coca-Cola said sorry kite
we got to stop sending you our 7x flavoring and he said but that is the secret
and they went I know and I'm really sorry but even though we're friends our
countries aren't friends right now and that was a huge
hit on Coca-Cola LLC gmbh Germany he couldn't make coke so he was like I got to
come up with a new plan yeah and also at the same time he's walking this this
fine line between not having access to the product that his company makes and
trying to keep the German government from officially seizing and taking over his
company and to do that he needs he needs a hit he needs the most delicious
most nutritious thing you could possibly put together that's going to sweep
Germany
right off right off the bat and I feel like we should talk about
this product that Max Keit introduced after a break
you
Okay, Chuck. So Max Kite's like, what am I going to do? I need to come up with
something fast to
keep my company afloat. I think I'll just create an entirely new drink that no
one's ever even
thought of making before. And because there's so many wartime rations going on,
I'm going to have
to get really creative here, but I'm going to do it. Yeah. I mean, not only did
he, was he not
getting that, that sweet, sweet 7X Coke syrup.
He didn't have sugar, or at least much.
They were rationing sugar at the time.
So he said, all right.
He ended up saying the recipe was made from the leftovers of the leftovers.
The first Fanta, which, by the way, is the German word for fantasy or
imagination.
And supposedly he said, hey, marketing team, use your fantasy to think of a good
name.
And they said, how about Fanta?
And he went, that's great.
How about Love Gun?
I think it was a guy named Joe Nip.
Who officially thought of the name, but he got apple pulp from leftover apple
cider making beet sugar and whey and by all accounts, it was not orange at all.
And it tasted like sweet garbage.
It's yeah, it took me a couple of reads to be like, well, wait a minute. How
does that taste like Fanta?
And then I realized with just sudden horror, it didn't taste anything like
Fanta.
And apparently it didn't taste very well at all.
Historians, no one knows what it tasted like, or at least no one's been able to
find somebody who actually drank this stuff.
But they're like, just look at the ingredients. There's no way it tasted good.
And they think that it was probably mostly sold to be used as like a flavor
agent for soups and stews and stuff like that.
That people weren't just knocking back bottles of this stuff because they would
have vomited until they died, I guess.
Instead, they were just using it in other ways.
But that's not to say it wasn't a huge hit.
It was a big seller.
And not only that, it instilled like a kind of national pride among Germans.
Like, look at how resourceful we are in the face of, you know, wartime scarcity.
But have you tried this stuff?
Yeah, it was their own.
They're like, we have Fanta and beer.
And like, we're going to claim those and love those and drink those until we
fall over.
So he did, even though, like I said, he officially supposedly never joined the
Nazi party, he did work very closely with the Nazi party because he needed their
help.
He needed their help making sure that production continued.
And, you know, the cooperation with the Nazis was a key part of that.
But that.
Was able to keep the doors open, at least officially Coca-Cola in April of 1955
postwar said, why don't we rejigger Fanta and make it taste good? And we've got
the name. We have it copyrighted and it's already sort of got a little bit of a
cred, at least in Europe. So let's just keep the name and hopefully no one will
remember the Nazi ties.
Yeah. But also, so this name.
Just the name, right? They could have come up with anything else, but just the
name is has Nazi ties.
Like you said, it was created in and for Nazi Germany, and it was also made from
apple pulp and beet sugar and whey.
Why would you use that? I would think you would want to do the exact opposite
and bury that name like it was a banner with the Coke logo and a swastika.
But instead, they just went with it and they introduced it in Italy first as
this, the version we know now, this orange soda version in Italy was like, yeah,
it's pretty good.
Let's go with that. And they started to export it, finally made it into the
United States in 1958, which was, I think, three years after they reintroduced
it in Italy.
Yeah, I think what the deal was, is it wasn't widely known outside of Germany.
So it's not like the word Fanta had some negative connotation all over the
world. And the Germans loved it. So it actually had a positive connotation in at
least one market. So, yeah, I get it. I mean, maybe it would have been a good PR
move to change it because it's a Nazi thing, but I don't think it was like some
otherwise tainted name.
I see.
I see what you mean. And they were like, I'm sure people will just forget about
it anyway within a year or two. Anybody who even knows about it, it'll never
come out.
Yeah. Until, you know, people started calling it a Nazi drink and, you know, on
the Internet.
Right.
And the idea kind of spread. And it was, you know, it was Fanta and not Fanta.
But, yeah, people largely didn't think much about it. And I still don't think
much about it. I mean, it's not like if you buy a Fanta.
Or something today, you're supporting Nazis, right?
It goes to the upkeep of Hitler's tomb or something like that.
A small donation.
But the author Pendergrast was like, it's this is pretty.
It is still pretty significant that people like this drink enough
that even knowing it's its roots or where it came from, you're just like,
it's just it's an orange soda.
I like it for what it is.
And it's not just orange.
As we said, they have a whole line of flavors, including grape.
Not Inappropriate or anything like that.
And I think it's much more popular in South America right now, but it's still
pretty big in America, in the United States.
Man, we keep getting taken to task for that, for calling the U.S. America.
Sorry, everybody.
That's what they tell us.
That's what they teach us here.
Yeah.
And hey, pretty soon, a lot of parts of the world are going to be called
America.
So get used to it, everyone.
As far as Kite goes, he stuck around and the Coca-Cola company said, you know
what, even though your drink was garbage, you did the yeoman's work way back
then and kept that brand alive.
And so he was made eventually the head of Coca-Cola Europe and, you know, seems
like had a pretty good career as a soda guy.
Oh, one other thing about that, too, is Kite, as the Nazis rolled into country
after country.
Kite was right behind the tanks going, your division of Coca-Cola is now part of
Coca-Cola Deutschland.
Your division of Coca-Cola is now part of Coca-Cola Deutschland.
And so when he was made the head of Coca-Cola Europe, he had consolidated
through conquering other businesses.
He had consolidated all into one company because of the Nazis conquering these
countries.
Isn't that nuts?
Yeah.
I mean, who better to lead the...
Coca-Cola Europe, you know, I guess he was already in place.
Yeah. He kept pounding his fist in his hand whenever he talked at like board
meetings and
investors meetings. That's right.
Okay. Well, that's it for Fanta. Do you want to Fanta? I don't know. That's only
a question
you can answer yourself. And while you think about that, we're done with this.
So short stuff is out.
Stuff You Should Know is a production of iHeartRadio.
For more podcasts from iHeartRadio, visit the iHeartRadio app, Apple Podcasts,
or wherever you listen to your favorite shows.